Part 5: Feeding Tubes
A feeding tube can be
placed in one of two ways,
through the nose and into the stomach,
or directly through the skin
into the stomach.
The first tube, through the nose
and into the stomach
is called a dobhoff tube.
The insertion of a tube
through the nose, through the esophagus,
and into the stomach is a procedure
that we can perform in the clinic.
It is a relatively quick procedure,
and the tube can be removed
easily as soon as eating food
by mouth is adequate
and your body weight has stabilized
and increased.
This tube is typically
a temporary solution
and can last for a few days
to a few weeks.
Dobhoff Tubes do not require a scheduled date or
overnight stay due to the relative simplicity of insertion.
The placement of a dobhoff tube
does not need image guidance.
However, after insertion of a dobhoff tube,
through the nose and into the stomach.
an X-ray of the chest will be taken
to confirm the proper placement
of the end of the tube
inside the stomach.
The second tube, directly through the skin
and into the stomach,
is called a Percutaneous Endogastric
Gastrostomy Tube  or Peg tube.
This tube is a more permanent intervention
and is surprisingly more common
than dobhoff tubes.
However, just because they're popular
doesn't mean they're good.
Compared to dobhoff tubes,
Peg tubes pose a greater number of
challenges with insertion and use.
First, the insertion of a peg tube
is somewhat more invasive than a
dobhoff tube. To be placed correctly,
The peg tube needs to be inserted
by a specialist called an
Interventional Radiologist,
with the assistance of image guidance.
PEG tubes can be placed in different ways
with varying degrees of invasiveness-
from image guidance, to minimal surgery
(laparoscopic), all the way to open surgery.
Open surgery is the most aggressive placement option.
Unlike Dobhoff Tubes, due to greater invasiveness,
PEG Tube Insertions cannot be performed in the clinic
and require both a scheduled and overnight stay.
Second, PEG tubes require a special
type of food called tube feeds.
Tube feeds are a different
composition from regular food.
Because of this,
your body will have to learn how to digest
this new food source
and may take several days.
Third, in addition to your body
learning this new food source,
you will also have to learn how,
when and where
to have tube feeds ordered and delivered.
Our dietitian will assist you
with this task.